{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Joseph Warren was killed at this battle as one side retreated across Charlestown Neck after running out of gunpowder, leaving their opponents with a Pyrrhic victory. During this battle, Israel Putnam allegedly ordered his troops not to fire until they saw the whites of their enemies’ eyes as British troops stormed a redoubt on Breed’s Hill. For ten points, name this Boston-area battle that followed Lexington and Concord.",
      "answer": "Battle of Bunker Hill A"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Tamworth Manifesto outlined the ideals of this modern political party. One prime minister from this party was a rival of William Gladstone and made Queen Victoria the “Empress of India.” Another prime minister from this party repealed the Corn Laws. This political party’s leaders included Benjamin Disraeli and founder Robert Peel. For ten points, name this British political party, sometimes called the Tories, that traditionally stands opposed to the Liberals and Labour.",
      "answer": "Conservative Party"
    },
    {
      "question": "The “Polyphase Phase” system was marketed under this man’s name, while the SI unit for magnetic fluxRdensity was named in his honor, 17 years after his 1943 death. George Westinghouse bought patents to this man’s induction motor, which prefaced Westinghouse’s company partaking in the “War of Currents” against the direct-current based Edison Electric Light Company. For ten points, name this Serbian-American who pioneered the use of alternating current systems.",
      "answer": "Nikola Tesla"
    },
    {
      "question": "Justice Scalia wrote that this practice was becoming “a game” after a ruling exempting the mentally disabled from it. The Court ruled that judges alone could not decide on this practice in Ring v. Arizona, Dand minors were exempted from it by Roper v. Simmons. Potential racial bias led the Supreme Court to declare laws on this practice too arbitrary in Furman v. Georgia, which was later overturned. For ten points, name this practice of executing those convicted of serious crimes.",
      "answer": [
        "Capital Punishment",
        "Death Penalty",
        "equivalents"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Dwight Evans spent all but one year of his career with this team, which fielded three generations of Hall of Fame left fielders in Jim Rice, Carl Yastrzemski, and “The Kid.” Pedro Martinez moved to this team from the Montreal Expos and helped the team end its championship drought of 86 years, allegedly caused by the team’s sale of Babe Ruth to a certain rival team based in New York. For ten points, name this Major League baseball team that plays its home games in Fenway Park.",
      "answer": "Boston Red Sox T"
    },
    {
      "question": "These people produced the Kunz Axe, a notably large ritual artifact made of jade that was consistent with the “were [WAIR]-jaguar motif” common in the art of these people. These people, the first to play the “ball game,” were also known as the “rubber people” for their ability to extract latex from trees. Their major sites included San Lorenzo and La Venta. For ten points, name this earliest known Meso-American F civilization noted for producing giant stone heads.",
      "answer": "Olmec"
    },
    {
      "question": "Thomas Allen’s song “Low Bridge” focuses on this structure whose creation was overseen by the “father of American Civil Engineering,” Benjamin Wright. Concerns arose that erosion of the Adirondack Mountainsmightdamagethisstructure,which,in1823,allowedlaborerstoreachtheNiagaraEscarpment. Containing thirty-four locks, this structure was originally traversed by long, thin vehicles known as packet A boats at speeds under 5 miles an hour. For ten points, name this New York canal.",
      "answer": "Erie Canal"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was forced to respond to the rebellion of Luis Mena by beginning a twenty year military intervention in Nicaragua. This man notably used a “Saxbe fix” to hire Philander Knox as his Secretary of State, appointing him to carry out “Dollar diplomacy.” This Republican split votes with the Bull Moose party’s Teddy Roosevelt in 1912, allowing Woodrow Wilson to become president. For ten points, name this man, the only person to serve both as president and Supreme Court justice. R",
      "answer": "William Howard Taft"
    },
    {
      "question": "This figure became embroiled in a scandal when telephone conversations with James Gilbey were leaked in “Squidgygate.” Much to the displeasure of Earl Howe, this “loose cannon” was photographed on a battleground in Angola as part of a campaign against the usage of landmines. The intoxication of Henri Paul may have inadvertently caused the death of Dodi Fayed and this figure in a tunnel at Pont de l’Alma. For ten points, name this first wife of Prince Charles who was killed in a 1997 car accident in Paris. D",
      "answer": [
        "Diana, Princess of Wales",
        "Princess Diana"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The fisherman Dictys took in this man and his mother after they were cast to sea in a wooden chest. This man received a magic wallet from Hermes and an invisibility helm from Hades. Grandfather to both Heracles and Helen of Troy, during one quest, this son of Danae stole a shared eye from the Gray Sisters. After killing a sea monster, this hero married Andromeda. For ten points, name this Greek hero who used a reflective shield during his slaying of Medusa.",
      "answer": "Perseus T"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The first European to inhabit what would become this city was Portuguese merchant Juan Rodriguez. Peter Minuit legendarily purchased the land for thisFcity from the Lenape [LEN-ah-peh] for 24 dollars worth of glass beads. Richard Nicholls captured this city from Director-General Peter Stuyvesant, and renamed this city from New Amsterdam to its present name. For ten points, name this city where traders founded a stock exchange under a buttonwood tree at Wall Street, which is on Manhattan Island.",
        "answer": [
          "New York City",
          "New Amsterdam before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Henry Hudson’s rediscovery of New York Harbor occurred while searching for what sea route from the Atlantic to the Pacific? A",
        "answer": "Northwest Passage"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This battle took place on a plain where the invading army attacked on the advice of the exiled Athenian tyrant Hippias. Prior to this battle, a request for aid was sent to Sparta, but due to the Carneia festival, the Spartans did not arrive until after this battle was over. In this battle, one thousand hoplites from Plataea reinforced the Athenians who were led by ten generals including Miltiades. For ten points, name this battle that thereafter named a distance race, the same length as the route run by the messenger Pheidippides. R",
        "answer": "Battle of Marathon"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Persian king during the Battle of Marathon was this man, the third King of Kings of the Achaemenid Empire and the father of Xerxes the Great.",
        "answer": [
          "Darius I",
          "Darius the Great"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "With a name from the Greek for “able to choose,” one of these groups called the Lollards was created by John Wycliffe. A campaign led by Simon de Montfort targeted one of these groups in Toulouse, D while another of these groups formed defensive squares with their wagons in battle. Examples of these groups include the Hussites, who were condemned at the Council of Constance, and the Cathars, who were attacked during the Albigensian Crusade. For ten points, name these historical groups that were persecuted for rejecting core Catholic beliefs.",
        "answer": [
          "Heretics",
          "word forms"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Hussites were based in Bohemia, the site of which is now found in what modern nation?",
        "answer": "Czech Republic"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A 1958 film about this battle starring John Mills and Richard Attenborough was partly based on the novel The Big Pick-Up. Another film about this battle was shot using very little CGI and twenty “Little Ships” which actually participated in this battle. That film about this battle, which was split into three sections named “The Sea,” “The Air,” and “The Mole,” starred Harry Styles and is widely considered to F be the best work of its director Christopher Nolan. For ten points, name this battle during which British and French forces were evacuated from France.",
        "answer": "Battle of Dunkirk"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Battle of Dunkirk occurred in this year, the same year as the Battle for the Hague, the Battle of Zeeland, and the beginning of the Battle of Britain.",
        "answer": "1940 A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country failed to capture Tangier after its King Edward’s brother encouraged him to attack the city from Ceuta. Rulers from this country’s House of Aviz sponsored Bartolomeu Dias’s expedition to the Cape of Good Hope and Vasco da Gama’s voyage to India. Along with Spain, this country signed the Treaty of Tordesillas, dividing up much of the New World. For ten points, name this country, whose Age of Discovery began in Lisbon.",
        "answer": "Portugal or Portuguese Empire BORNUS: This son of John I of Portugal is considered the instigator of the Portuguese Age of Discovery. ANSWER: Prince Henry the Navigator 6 In one novel written in this language, Marius joins the Friends of the ABC. In another novel originally written in this language, Athos, Porthos, and Aramis form the title group, who adopt the motto “All for one, one for all.” The Three Musketeers was originally written in it, as was a novel where the gypsy Esmeralda is rescued by the deformed Quasimodo. For ten points, name this language which Victor Hugo used to pen Les Miserables and The Hunchback of Notre Dame. D ANSWER: French"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another author who wrote in French, Jules Verne, is known as the “Father” of this speculative genre, as exemplified by his books Journey to the Center of the Earth and Twenty Thousand Leagues Under the Sea.",
        "answer": "Science fiction T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After this man arbitrated for Paraguay to receive what is now sixty percent of the nation, a department in Paraguay was named in his honor. During his time with Ohio’s 23rd Regiment in the Civil War, this man was wounded at the Battle of South Mountain and served alongside another future president, William McKinley. He was the first man to win three elections as Governor of Ohio but required F a little assistance from Congress to win election to higher office. For ten points, who ended Reconstruction upon becoming President after the Compromise of 1877?",
        "answer": "Rutherford B. Hayes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Hayes was awarded twenty disputed electoral votes as part of the Compromise of 1877, thus defeating what Democrat Presidential candidate?",
        "answer": "Samuel J. Tilden A"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Presidency of John Adams",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Man for whom he served as Vice President F",
          "answer": "George Washington"
        },
        {
          "question": "Republican he defeated to win the presidency",
          "answer": "Thomas Jefferson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Election year in which he defeated that man",
          "answer": "1796 A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Vice President during Adams’s term, whose brother Charles would be nominated in 1800",
          "answer": "Thomas Pinckney"
        },
        {
          "question": "Undeclared naval war with France fought largely in the Caribbean during Adams’s administration",
          "answer": "Quasi-War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Set of 1798 laws he passed restricting freedom of speech and delaying the time before an immigrant could become a citizen R",
          "answer": "Alien and Sedition Acts prompt if only one is given"
        },
        {
          "question": "Resolution drafted by James Madison to counter that legislation",
          "answer": [
            "Virginia Resolution",
            "Kentucky and Virginia Resolutions, in any order"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Secretary of State who was dismissed after an argument about sending another peace delegation to France",
          "answer": "Timothy Pickering D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Battle of the Bulge",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country that launched their final major offensive to begin the battle F",
          "answer": [
            "Nazi Germany",
            "Deutschland"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Supreme Allied Commander during the battle who later became President of the United States",
          "answer": "Dwight David “Ike” Eisenhower"
        },
        {
          "question": "Colorful commander of the U.S. Third Army who led the counterattack that relieved the 101st Airborne A",
          "answer": [
            "George S. Patton III",
            "George S. Patton Jr."
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Heavily forested region of Belgium and Luxembourg where the battle took place",
          "answer": "Ardennes Forest"
        },
        {
          "question": "British commander who took charge of the northern half of the defense during this battle",
          "answer": "Bernard Law Montgomery"
        },
        {
          "question": "Besieged key road junction defended by the 101st Airborne Division during this battle R",
          "answer": "Bastogne"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Germans named the battle “Operation Watch on” this 2nd longest central European river",
          "answer": "Rhine"
        },
        {
          "question": "One-word response of Brigadier General Anthony McAuliffe to a surrender demand",
          "answer": "Nuts D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Polar exploration",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Icy continent where the South Pole is located F",
          "answer": "Antarctica"
        },
        {
          "question": "Norwegian explorer who led the first expedition to reach the South Pole",
          "answer": "Roald Amundsen"
        },
        {
          "question": "British explorer who died while returning from the South Pole after a failed rendezvous with dog teams A",
          "answer": "Robert Falcon Scott"
        },
        {
          "question": "Explorer whose ship Endurance was crushed by ice, forcing a journey aboard lifeboats to South Georgia",
          "answer": "Ernest Shackleton"
        },
        {
          "question": "American companion of Matthew Henson on the first expedition to reach the North Pole",
          "answer": "Robert Peary 6RAmerican nuclear submarine which made the first submerged transit of the North Pole ANSWER: USS Nautilus"
        },
        {
          "question": "American aviator who claimed to be the first to reach both poles by air",
          "answer": "Richard E. Byrd"
        },
        {
          "question": "Danish-born Russian sailor whose Great Northern Expedition mapped the Arctic coast",
          "answer": "Vitus Bering D T"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One politician described this law as a “title page to a great, tragic volume.” John Taylor and Jesse Thomas introduced many parts of thFis law that was described as a (20 pts)",
        "“Fire bell in the night” by Thomas Jefferson. James Tallmadge attempted to add a proposal to this law that would have made children of slaves free after the age of 25. This law led to the (10 pts)",
        "formation of Maine as a free state and was declared unconstitutional in Dred Scott v. Sanford. For ten points, name this 1820 law that allowed slavery above the 36-30 line."
      ],
      "answer": "Missouri Compromise"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this modern-day country, the 21 Demands of MKS were hung on Ostrow Island in A August, 1980. A leader of this nation declared martial law at least partially in response to a (20 pts)",
        "strike orchestrated by a union founded in Lenin Shipyard. One president of this nation won the 1983 Nobel Peace Prize based on his work founding the (10 pts)",
        "Solidarity trade union in Gdansk. For ten points, name this country where president Lech Walesa was the first democratically elected leader to govern from Warsaw."
      ],
      "answer": "Poland or Polish People’s Republic"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A kingdom ruled by people of this ethnic group was first described by William Elliot GrRiffis using the term “hermit kingdom” to describe their isolationist policy. These people repelled an invasion led by (20 pts)",
        "Toyotomi Hideyoshi under the leadership of Yi Sun-sin. King Sejong the Great, a ruler from the Joseon dynasty. introduced the phonetic alphabet used by these people, (10 pts)",
        "Hangul. For ten points, name these people who mainly live in one of two namesake countries that have capitals at Pyongyang and Seoul."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Koreans",
        "Joseonminjok before mentioned,",
        "Hanminjok"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man boasted that defeating the British would be as easy as eating breakfast. This Dman refused to reinforce La Haye Sainte, and his cannons were nullified by the reverse slope defense. A fatal charge by (20 pts)",
        "Marshal Ney against retreating Englishmen was ordered by this man. This man deployed his troops from Plancenoit in order to capture Hougoumont but was hampered by the late arrival of Gebhard von Blucher at this man’s (10 pts)",
        "final defeat. For ten points, name this Frenchman who died 1200 miles off the west coast of Africa on the island of Saint Helena."
      ],
      "answer": "Napoleon Bonaparte"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man won the Mallian campaign, personally killing their leader but sustaining a nearly fatal arrow wound in the process. Previously, this man had defeated Ariobarzanes at the Battle of the Persian Gates and Batis at the Siege of (20 pts)",
        "Gaza. This man led the charge which won the Battle of Chaeronea, and his other victories include the Battle of the Granicus River, the Battle of Issus, and the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Gaugamela, where he defeated King Darius III of Persia and brought an end to the Persian empire. For ten points, name this Macedonian conqueror."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Alexander the Great",
        "Alexander III of Macedon T"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one number, this character tells another “you’re driving me to homicide” because he has not seen his wife in six months. In another, this character is told about “how the speculators won” and “how the war vets lost” in the Off-Broadway version of (20 pts)",
        "“What’d I Miss.” In “Washington on Your Side”, this character vows to “show these Federalists what F they’re up against” with James Madison and (10 pts)",
        "Aaron Burr. For ten points, name this character from 1776 and Hamilton whose running mate was Aaron Burr in the Election of 1800 in which he was elected the third U.S. president."
      ],
      "answer": "Thomas Jefferson"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A monument displaying a boot belonging to this man honors his best known victory, though he was less successful leading a siege of Quebec during which his leg was severely A injured for the first time. This man was forced to flee aboard the ship (20 pts)",
        "Vulture after meeting with Major John Andre, an action prompted by this man’s anger that he had not received credit for helping (10 pts)",
        "win the Battle of Saratoga. For ten points, name this general who planned to transfer Fort Ticonderoga to the British, whose name is now a synonym for “traitor.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Benedict Arnold"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While flying above this feature in 1956, TWA and United Airlines planes crashed in mid-air. A tribe known for inhabiting this region has a name translating as “blue-green waRter people.” Before becoming a Senator, Ralph (20 pts)",
        "Cameron improved a hiking path along this feature that became known as the Bright Angel Trail. The Hopi House is located on the South Rim of this feature that is formed by the Kaibab Limestone. John (10 pts)",
        "Wesley Powell’s expedition down the Colorado River took him through the entire length of, for ten points, what natural feature in Arizona?"
      ],
      "answer": "Grand Canyon"
    }
  ]
}